{"tossups": [{"question": "In an effort to encourage dental health, this leader encouraged his population to chew on bones because dogs do so. This leader renamed the month of September after his book<em> Ruhnama</em>, whose study is required to obtain a driver\u2019s license in his country. This leader commissioned the construction of an Arch of Neutrality, which contained a golden statue of himself that rotated to face the sun in the city of Ashgabat. For ten points, name this totalitarian ruler of post-independence Turkmenistan from 1991 to his death in 2006.", "answer": "Saparmurat<b> Niyazov</b> (or<b> Turkmenbashi</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The fourth and final section of a book by this man incorrectly tries to explain the origins of Earth\u2019s tides. This man supported one of his arguments by citing the phases of Venus and apparent motion of sunspots. This man introduced the idea of inertial reference frames with a thought experiment about a man below deck on a ship, and wrote a book consisting of conversations between the laymen Sagredo, Simplicio, and Salviati. For ten points, name this author of a<em> Diologue Concerning the Two Chief World</em> <em>Systems</em>, who was charged with heresy for supporting heliocentrism.", "answer": "<b> Galileo Galilei</b> (accept either underlined name)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "An activist from this country mysteriously died while on a U-Boat heading towards his home country during Operation Dove. During World War II, this country was governed by the Emergency Powers Act while maintaining official neutrality. The SS<em> Libau</em> was intercepted before it could supply arms to supporters of an uprising in this modern-day country. Roger Casement was executed for treason as a revolutionary for, for ten points, what country that was led by Eamon de Valera, who fought during the 1916 Easter Rising?", "answer": "<b> Ireland</b> (or<b> Eire</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In a battle in this province, Zhang Shijie was tricked by music to think that the enemy had a banquet. The Battle of Yamen occurred in this southern province, where the Hong factories operated prior to the Opium Wars. The Pearl River Delta lies in this province, which borders the special administrative regions of Hong Kong and Macau. The most populous province in China is, for ten points, what region that contains a city once known as Canton?", "answer": "<b> Guangdong</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Marie van Goethem worked in this profession and, at age 14, served as a model for a bronze sculpture with a wax-covered skirt. A bronze statuette of a girl wearing bangles was found in Mohenjo-daro in 1926 and is named for this assumed activity. This action is depicted in statutes of Shiva<em> nataraja</em>, in which the god is encircled by a ring of fire with one leg raised. For ten points, name this activity depicted in Edgar Degas paintings of women practicing at the barre or performing in ballets.", "answer": "<b> dancing</b> (accept anything related to<b> dance</b>, including<b> ballet</b>; accept Little<b> Dancer</b> of Fourteen Years; accept<b> Dancing Girl</b>; accept Cosmic<b> Dancer</b> and similar)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This scientist led a task force that outlined plans for a permanent lunar base and a manned mission to Mars in a strategic initiative regarding \u201cAmerica\u2019s Future in Space.\u201d Donald Kutyna was leaked internal documents by this figure, who sat with him on the Rogers Commission. This astronaut was insultingly asked \u201cWill the flight affect your reproductive organs?\u201d before a mission aboard the<em> Challenger</em>. For ten points, name this astronaut, the first American woman in space.", "answer": "Sally<b> Ride</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "In 1969, protesters at this university advocated the creation of a Black Studies program during the Allen Building Takeover. This university\u2019s president, Terry Sanford, tried to place the Richard Nixon Presidential Library at this school, which was initially founded by Quakers and Methodists in the town of Trinity. One namesake of this school fought the Black Patch Wars and bought Lucky Strike as head of the American Tobacco Company. For ten points, name this private university in Durham, North Carolina.", "answer": "<b> Duke</b> University", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This thinker argued that totemic religions played a large part in developing the collective consciousness of a people in his<em> Rules of the Sociological Method</em>. In one study, this man pointed to stronger Catholic social controls as diminishing a phenomenon that he divided into egoistic, altruistic, fatalistic, and anomic types. Auguste Comte inspired, for ten points, what author of<em> Elementary Forms of Religious Life</em> and <em>Suicide</em>, a French pioneer of sociology?", "answer": "Emile<b> Durkheim</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This initiative may have led to the murder of exiled president Jango Goulart. As part of this initiative, Celestina Almada was forced to listen to her husband Martin\u2019s torture over telephone, prompting a search for documentation of this initiative in the Archives of Terror. Manuel Contreras was one of the early masterminds of this initiative, which was originally run by the DINA secret police but soon expanded to include Jorge Videla\u2019s Dirty War in Argentina. For ten points, name this 1970s-era operation in which South American governments silently eliminated communist dissidents.", "answer": "Operation<b> Condor</b> (do not accept or prompt on Dirty War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In the<em> Aeneid</em>, a god of this domain was the father of Circe, the mother of Latinus. A Roman emperor who worshiped a god of this domain controversially took the Vestal Virgin Aquilia Severa as his fourth wife; that emperor, who gave his name to a deity of this domain, was Elagabalus. A cult centered around an \u201cunconquered\u201d deity of this domain was popular in the Roman Empire until the 4th century. For ten points, give this domain of the deities Sol Invictus and Helios.", "answer": "<b> sun</b> (accept<b> Sol</b> before read)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "The operation to kill Osama bin Laden was codenamed for, for ten points, what Apache warchief whose name is sometimes exclaimed by jumping paratroopers?", "answer": "<b> Geronimo</b> (accept<b> Goyahkla</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s writings detail Eadburh\u2019s [ed-buh\u2019s] accidental poisoning of her husband Beorhtric [be-oh-trik]. This man, the primary source for the Battle of Ashdown, helped</b> <b>his patron translate Pope Gregory I\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Pastoral Care, which became the oldest extant</b> <b>book written in English. This man\u2019s most famous work documented the subject\u2019s defeat of Guthrum, creation of the (*)</b> Danelaw, and rule as King of Wessex. For ten points, name this Welsh bishop who wrote the biography<em> Life of King Alfred</em>.", "answer": "Bishop<b> Asser</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This composer called for a piano with lutheal attachment in his violin rhapsody</b><em><b> Tzigane</b></em><b>. In 1910, this man orchestrated a piece meant to evoke a dancing infanta in Baroque-era</b> <b>Spain. A pair of brothers killed by the same shell in (+)</b> <b>World War I were eulogized in a</b> <b>\u201cRiguadon\u201d this composer included as part of his</b><em><b> Tombeau de Couperin</b></em><b>. This composer of </b><em><b>Pavane for a Dead Princess</b></em><b> also wrote a (*)</b> repetitive piece for Ida Rubenstein consisting of one long crescendo. For ten points, name this French composer of<em> Bolero</em>.", "answer": "Maurice<b> Ravel</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In this state, after the Cockstock Incident, African Americans were banned from residing here and could be punished by Burnett\u2019s Lash law. John McLoughlin was a \u201cfather\u201d of this</b> <b>state while working in the Hudson\u2019s Bay Company. Under James (+)</b> <b>Polk, this region of</b> <b>the United States claimed by Great Britain was annexed in an 1846 Treaty that did not extend the border to (*)</b> 54-40. Lewis and Clark founded Fort Clatsop in this state, the end of their journey to the Pacific Ocean. A namesake trail led to the Willamette Valley in, for ten points, what modern Pacific Northwest state?", "answer": "<b> Oregon</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Edward Aethling was brought up in the court of this man\u2019s wife Gisela of Bavaria. This man\u2019s right hand became part of a cult and was stolen by Mercurius. This ruler was either crowned on Christmas or New Year\u2019s Day with a crown from Pope Sylvester II. This Grand</b> <b>Prince succeeded (+)</b> <b>G\u00b4eza and created the Archbishopric of Esztergom. To take power,</b> <b>this man killed the (*)</b> Magyar prince Kopp\u00b4any, who ruled the region near Lake Balaton. Ladislaus I began the canonization campaign for this Arpad ruler and saint. For ten points, name this first Christian king of Hungary.", "answer": "Saint<b> Stephen</b> I", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>During this war, the USS</b><em><b> Baltimore</b></em><b> destroyed the city of Iloilo [ee-lo-ee-lo] just hours after soldiers were killed in Santa Mesa. During this war, Jacob Smith wanted to create</b> <b>\u201ca howling wilderness\u201d and ordered his soldiers to kill everyone over the (+)</b> <b>age of ten.</b> <b>Frederick Funston pretended to be the prisoner of indigenous Macabebe scouts during this war; that trick allowed for the capture of (*)</b> Emilio Aguinaldo. For ten points, name this war in which American forces put down the Tagalog Republic.", "answer": "<b> Philippine</b>-American War (accept<b> Filipino</b>-American War; accept<b> Tagalog Insurgency</b>, <b>Revolt</b>, etc. before \u201cTagalog\u201d is said) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>During this man\u2019s time as prime minister, Francis Atterbury was found to be in</b> <b>a Jacobite plot. Riots in Edinburgh occurred in this man\u2019s premiership, after John</b> <b>Porteous killed several civilians. George (+)</b> <b>Grenville and William Pitt the Elder</b> <b>opposed this man with the \u201cBoy Patriots.\u201d This prime minister lost power during the</b> <b>War of (*)</b> Jenkins\u2019 Ear. This Whig gained power during the South Sea Bubble. For ten points, name this longest-holding and first prime minister of Great Britain.", "answer": "Robert<b> Walpole</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}